# SAPAN RAVAL

141 Farrington Ave | Norfolk, MA 02056 | T: 201.208.4988 | Email: sapanraval@gmail.com

# TECHNICAL PRODUCT OWNER

Highly driven and results-oriented business product owner and system analyst with 12 years of project management, technology, operations management, and product development experience. Proven record of success with technical intensive performance centric business projects. Known for strategic project realignment to meet core objectives with delivery within budget constraints and meeting schedules. Project leader with operations and engineering management background. Verifiable success in limiting risks, creating lean teams, and creative strategies for optimizing internal operations and financial returns. Excellent communication skills and ability to develop compelling presentations tailored for internal and external consumption.

## **CORE COMPETENCIES**

- Product Line Strategic Planning
- Market Segmentation and Competitive Analysis
- Operational Metric Development and Reporting
- · Business Process Modelling

- Develop and Lead Product Management
- . Complete Product Life Cycle Management
- New Business and Segment Development
- Competitive Analysis

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## LIBERTY MUTUAL INVESTMENTS, Boston, MA

2014 - Present

Principal Systems Analyst

Gather requirements and drive the team toward delivering product through using Agile methodology, while meeting targets and preserving client value and quality by heading project meetings. Administer the product backlog, devise an effective vision, and deliver timely stakeholder feedback on development iterations. Facilitate end users to transfer out 1400+ holdings from LMI accounting system. Determine acceptance criteria and devise test scenarios/plans and perform user acceptance test (UAT) by collaborating with users.

- Successfully transferred 5000+ holdings from Ironshore to LMI accounting system to complete the acquisition.
- Enhanced overall system performance through utilizing job scheduler (Active Batch) to schedule jobs and automated workflow.
- Executed the application and amplify overall system performance by working with cross-functional teams, end users, and vendors.
- Improved and headed investment operations, controls, data flow, and reporting by business analysis/product management for systems.
- Evaluated the business processes for inefficiencies and suggested recommendations for solutions or improvements by assisting new product development leader.
- Accelerated internal procedural operations by working on different financial products such as Common Stock, Bonds, MBS Securities, Fixed Income, and TBAs etc., while understanding workflows, processes, and data across environments, and contribution.
- Articulated data analysis and identify root cause by sustaining production environment, troubleshooting problem, and working on complex MS SQL queries.

#### OMGEO, LLC, Boston, MA

2011 - 2014

Business Analyst

Delivered product, while attaining targets and objectives of the project and keeping client's value and quality – e.g., delivering minimal viable product by participating in client meetings to gather requirements and driving the team towards the fastest way. Spearheaded and participated in the agile iteration planning meeting, showcase, and other agile ceremonies. Collaborated and liaised between business users and different teams involved in the post-trade settlement and central matching application development. Worked on post-trade settlement and matching solution for financial products such as Equity, Fixed Income, and REPOs.

- Built the technical developments throughout a series of rapid iterations by implementing an iterative a gile methodology and work with the customers and the developers.
- Assessed business requirements and formulated concise and effective user stories.
- Refined product backlog items and updated key performance indicators (KPIs) based on value after delivery of each increment to end users by assisting end users and the development team.

## THOMSON REUTERS, Milwaukee, WI

2009 - 2011

**Business Analyst** 

Established UML diagrams using MS Visio, and formalized user guides and client presentations for the deployment of new functionality by preparing functional specification/business requirement documents. Derived the business specification document and facilitated in preparation of system requirement specifications by serving as a business analyst and analyzing business requirements. Planned and executed business strategy by participated in and facilitated different levels of discussions through JAD sessions and business workshops held.

- Designed internal SharePoint site and migrated documents from the shared drive to SharePoint environment.
- Ensured accuracy and meet deadlines by coordinating and prioritizing outstanding defects and enhancement/system requests based on business requirements and allowing sufficient time frame.

# STATE STREET CORPORATION, Boston, MA

2006 - 2009

Business Systems Analyst

Spearheaded various projects including leading client facilitation meetings to gather requirements and work on business requirements by analyzing/designing architecture by using Rational Unified Process (RUP) Methodology. Worked on various applications such a Global Transaction Manager, Global Reference System and Instruct Trade Order manager systems.

• Prepared vision documents, usecase documents, functional specifications, user interface specifications, and UML diagrams by using MS Visio and Rational Rose tools.

## **EDUCATION CREDENTIALS**

UNIVERSITY OF BRIDGEPORT, Bridgeport, CT | 2006

Master of Business Administration

GUJARAT UNIVERSITY, Gujrat, India | 2004

Master of Commerce in Accounting

GUJARAT UNIVERSITY, Gujarat, India | 2002

Bachelor of Commerce in Accounting

GENERAL ASSEMBLY, Boston, MA | 2018

Front-End Web Development

SCRUM.ORG | 2018

Professional Scrum Product Owner I (PSPO I)

SCRUM.ORG | 2018

Professional Scrum Master I (PSM I)

#### TECHNICAL PROFICIENCY

Methodology: Scrum, Kanban, Lean, XP, RUP, Waterfall
Requirement Management Tools: Microsoft Word, Excel, Powerpoint, Rational Requisite Pro
Management Tools: Microsoft Project, JIRA, SharePoint, Active Batch
Data Analysis Tools: MS Excel & Access, SQL Management Studio,
Designing Tools: Power BI, SQL Server Reporting Services (SSRS), Microsoft Visio
Development: C, HTML5, CSS, jQuery, JavaScript